Hey, hey, what's up my friend? So,
here's the thing, right? If trading is
80% psychology, then monks will be rich.
If trading is about discipline, then
soldiers they will rule Wall Street. And
if risk management alone work, then
nobody will blow up their trading
account. So clearly something is missing
and this is what today's video is about,
right? I'll share with you why 95% of
traders lose and how to be in the top 1%
of traders. First, let's provide some
context. Over the last 5 years, the S&P
500 has returned about 90%. So what this
means is that if you made less than 90%
over the last 5 years, if your
portfolio, your account made less than
90% over the last 5 years, it means you
didn't beat the markets. But if you made
more than 90% over the last 5 years,
you're probably in the top 5% of
traders. And if you made sub
substantially more than 90%, maybe 120
150%, you're likely in the top 1% of
traders.
The reason I'm sharing this is because
anyone can talk about, you know, beating
the markets, being in the top 5% of
traders, top 1% of traders, but talk is
cheap. What about results? So, this is
why to prove to you that whatever I'm
sharing with you works in the real world
of trading. This is my own life trading
results taken from my brokerage account.
So, you can see over here over the last
about 7 years, the green line is my
trading account equity curve. My account
is up about 343% versus 118% for the S&P
500. You can see this over here. Now,
I'm showing this to you not to brag, but
rather to let you know that the things
that you're about to learn in today's
video are the same strategies and
concepts that I apply to my own live
account. So, here is what you'll learn
today. Number one, we'll talk about why
most traders struggle even if they are
smart, hardworking, or motivated. like
no matter what they do, somehow they're
just not getting ahead. Why is that?
Next, I'll share with you how to
actually put the odds in your favor to
be in the top 5%, the top 1% of traders
even, so you can profit in bull and bare
markets, even during a recession. Then
I'll share with you what it takes to
become a profitable trader, no matter
what stage you're at, whether you've
been losing for years or break even for
the longest time. I'll give you the
exact blueprint so you know what it
takes to become a profitable trader. And
finally, you'll discover that, you know,
profitable trading is not as complicated
as it seems. But at the same time, it's
also not what you think. Sounds good?
Then hit the subscribe button and let's
get to it.
To kick things off, right, here's why
95% of traders lose. And of course there
are many reasons for it but based on my
interaction and educa educating of
traders over the years these are the top
few reasons why most traders lose.
Number one you don't have a proven
strategy. And I can't really blame you
for it because nowadays with social
media you know things like Facebook,
YouTube, LinkedIn X.
There's so much information out there.
You get information overload. One
trading guru says breakout is the way.
Another one says no you got to wait for
a pullback. let the market come to you.
And another guy says, "No, you got to
look at the stars, Raina. Look at the
moon for buy and sell signals.
Astrology, baby." Now, at this point,
you feel overwhelmed. Every mother, son,
daughter out there is telling you that
their strategy works. How do you know
what works? How do you know what doesn't
work? And if you do not know what works
then how do you develop the or rather
how do you develop the conviction to
follow the rules of your trading system.
This then brings you to the next problem
strategy hopping. So this is where you
hop from one strategy to the next with
the hopes of finding something better
finding the holy grail. And it happened
to me as well right early on in my
trading career. The first strategy that
I was taught or I came about was using
Ballinger bands. You know, wait for the
price to come towards the lower
Ballinger band, buy near the lows of the
Ballinger band and then sell when it
makes a bounce higher. You know, buy
low, sell high. And when I trade this
strategy at the start, you know, I had
like three or four winning trades in a
row. And I thought to myself, man, I'm
going to retire by 30, baby. I'm going
to buy a villa and have a nice swimming
pool in my villa by 30. And now I'm
almost 40 years old. There's no villa,
there's no swimming pool, but having
three monkeys running around in my
house. So anyway, eventually right while
trading this strategy, I encountered a
few losses, a series of losses. And
that's when I think maybe this strategy
isn't working anymore. Let me move on to
something better. Then I tried trading
indicators, you know, RSI, MACD,
Fibonacci, and again winning trades at
the start followed by a series of
losers. And then that's where I have my
conviction shattered and I look for the
next best thing. So I tried chart
patterns, harmonic patterns and this
whole cycle will rinse repeat itself.
And the only pattern that I was good at
recognizing is that my trading account
balance is going down in a downtrend.
You don't need any indicators for that
is and it's a 100% winning rate. Yeah.
So it's like going to the gym, right?
For one week. One week you do strength
training, then you see not no results.
You go and do high rocks, no results.
You do CrossFit, then you switch to yoga
and you're all over the place. Your
actions are inconsistent. And when your
actions are inconsistent, that's where
you get inconsistent results.
And this is why, right, when you have no
proven strategy, you don't have
conviction. And this will naturally lead
you to strategy hopping. And this brings
me to the third reason why traders lose.
lack of discipline. And what's
interesting is that many traders, they
think that they have a discipline
problem. They think that they have a
trading psychology problem. But I'm here
to tell you that 80% 90% of you watching
this video now, if you feel that you
have a discipline problem, I want to say
that you don't have a discipline
problem. Why do I say that? That's
because most of your discipline
problems stems from not having a proven
strategy. Let me explain. Imagine this.
Imagine you have this very special coin
and I give you this special coin. And
every time the coin comes up heads,
let's say it comes up heads, you win $2.
And if it comes up tails, you lose a
dollar. Now, let me ask you, will you
have a discipline problem? Will you have
the fear of tossing the coin? Let's say
you toss the coin and you have lost
three, four times in a row. Will you
struggle with that discipline to toss
that coin because you lost three times
in a row? Will you abandon the coin
after five losses in a row? Of course
not, right? You will flip this damn coin
as often as you can. Morning, night,
dinner, in the toilet, when you're
peeing, you know, you're flipping your
bird, you're also flipping the coin.
Why? Because the coin is a money maker.
Does it make sense? So this is why
whatever discipline problem that you're
facing right now, it's likely because
you don't have a proven strategy that
works. You don't have something that you
believe in that will yield you a
positive outcome, a profit in the long
run. And that's why you struggle with
your discipline. Next,
emotions. Many traders lose because of
emotions. Let me give you an example.
Imagine this. you you buy a stock and
within 3 days the stock price went up
50%. And you're all over the moon,
right? So at this point, do you do you
sell or do you hold? For many of you,
you would hold, right? Because you think
to yourself, man, Raina, this is just
just the start of a new uptrend. I'm
going to hold the stock, man. Let me get
it to 100% and sell. It looks a lot
better. So, you decided to hold that
stock. And shortly afterwards, the next
day, the stock price makes a pullback.
Now, from a 50% gain, you're now only at
a 40% gain because he made a pullback.
And you think to yourself, hm, I got to
hold this trade because this is how
winners are made, right? Tough time
don't last. Tough men do. So, you hold
the stock.
And what happens next is that the
pullback became a reversal. The stock
price goes back all the way to your
entry price. So, you've just witnessed a
50% profit
comes back down to your entry price and
you don't have a profit anymore and you
start to feel lousy about yourself and
you tell yourself, "Okay, I'm not going
to be greedy anymore. If the stock makes
a bounce, a 5 10% bounce, I'm taking
profits. At least I got again a profit.
Better than nothing." But guess what?
The stock somehows doesn't want to
listen to you. It continues to go down
lower lower and now you're in the red.
At this point, you're feeling
uncomfortable. You watch a winning
trade. It becomes a break even trade and
now it's a losing trade. You have no
choice. You don't want to take the pain
any longer and you cut your loss.
Yeah. And then shortly afterwards,
another trading opportunity comes along.
You buy another stock and within one day
the stock went up 5%. And you quickly
sell. You sell it even faster, right?
than me running away when my wife says,
"Honey, we need to talk." You sell the
stock. And if you think about this,
right, why does this happen? Well, it
happens because of fear and greed. The
first trade, you were greedy. You wanted
more and you watch the stock price
reverse back to your entry price and,
you know, put you in the red. The second
trade, there was fear, the fear of
losing, right? You've just experienced
what is like, you know, losing your open
open profit. So, you quickly sell that
stock because of fear. And for the
second trade, you know usually what
happens. The moment you sell, the stock
price doubles the next week. Agree? And
this happens because of a simple reason.
It happens because you don't have rules.
You don't have objective rules to tell
you when to buy and sell. And if you
don't trade with rules, you're going to
be relying on your emotions to tell you
when to get in and get out. And by now,
you should know that if you rely on
emotions to buy and sell, it's usually
at the worst possible time. And this is
why many traders right they lose when
they rely on their emotions. And because
of emotions it will also cause you to
revenge trade overtrading doubling down
on your losses. Right? After a series of
losses after losing consistently the
market can seems like it's out to get
you. Things get personal. You have
thoughts like you know why is the market
always out to get me? Why does it always
hunt my stop-loss? Why does it always
reverse the moment I hit buy? Then you
get angry. Some of them might even say
things like, you know, let me show you
who's boss, right? How dare you do this
to me? So, this is where traders, they
average down into into their losses.
They revenge trade. They widen their
stop loss. And that's how traders blow
up. Yeah. So all these trading mistakes
that I've shared with you over here,
these are what I call symptoms. Okay,
they are not the cause. So what do I
mean by this? Let me explain. So these
are symptoms and not the cause. So a
simple analogy is that let's say you
forget your wife birthday or her wedding
anniversary or your wedding anniversary
whatever, right? Let's say you forget
about it and your wife started to behave
in a funny manner. You know, she say
things to you like, you know,
honey, we need to talk. And you ask her,
are you all right? I'm fine. Don't touch
me. Go away. Those are symptoms. Yeah,
symptoms. There's something underlying
that cause her to behave in this manner.
And that underlying cause is because you
forget your wedding anniversary, you
forget your birthday and whatnot. So,
same thing for trading, right? All this
over here they are symptoms they are not
the cause. There is something
missing that traders lack that cause
them to behave in this manner.
So now what
are the cause behind it?
To answer this question I ask myself
what do the top 5% of traders have in
common? What do profitable traders have
in common? That's because profitable
traders, traders who can profit
consistently, they can manage their
emotions. They can remain disciplined
and that's how they extract profits from
the market in the long run.
So what I found out is this. I found out
that all profitable traders, they have
three things in common. And it doesn't
matter whether you're an options trader,
crypto trader, systems trader, price
action trader, day trader, you must have
these three things. If not, you will
never make it. So, let me explain to you
what these three things are. Number one,
you must have an H in the markets. So,
an H is something that you do repeatedly
over time that yields a positive
outcome. So, let me give you an example.
Imagine this. Imagine you toss a coin
and every time if the coin comes up
head, you win $2. And every time it
comes up tails, you lose a dollar. Let
me ask you, in the long run, will you
make money or lose money?
You're probably thinking, well, Rainer,
that's a no-brainer. You will make
money. Yeah, exactly. You will make
money in the long run because your
winners is larger than your losses. At
the same time, have a look at this
example.
Now, this time we inverse it. Every time
it comes up, you win $1. And if it comes
up tails, you lose $2. In the long run,
will you win or lose? Well, in the long
run, you will lose because you don't
have an edge in this coin toss. Now,
here's the thing, right? In trading,
your winning rate is not always 50%. So,
if it's 50%, it's easy to tell when you
have an H and when you don't have an H.
But what if in trading you have a
winning rate of 40%, 60%, how do you
know whether you have an H or not? So,
this is where I'm going to share with
you how to actually define an H. So it
can be broken down into a very simple
formula which is this E which stands for
expectancy which stands for an H is
winning percentage multiply by your
average gain minus your losing
percentage multiply by your average
loss. So let me explain. So your winning
percentage is very simple. If out of 10
trades you win six trades that is a 60%
winning rate. Your average gain
similar concept. If you made $1,000
after 10 trades then your average gain
per trade is $100. just 1,000 divid by
10 you get 100. So that's how you
calculate this figures over here. And
once you have those figures, you can
then plug it in to find out whether your
strategy, whether your system gives you
an edge in the markets. Here's an
example. So if you look at this, let's
say you have a trading system that has a
70% winning rate and your average gain
each time you win on average is about
$80.
you have a 30% losing rate. Just 100%
minus 70% will give you your losing
rate, which is 30%. And let's say your
average loss is $100. So in this case,
you can see that your average loss is
bigger than your average gain. So for
traders who are familiar with the term
risk-to-reward, you can see that your
risk-to-reward ratio is is not even a
1:1, right? You're risking let's say a
dollar and coming back to make 80 cents
on average. Less than a one to1
risk-to-reward ratio.
So is this a profitable trading system
in the long run? So again plug in the
numbers. So over here
0.7 which is your winning rate multiply
by 80 which is your average gain minus
0.3 which is your losing rate multiply
by 100 which is your average loss and
you get $26. So what does this $26 mean?
So if your E over here, your expectancy,
your H is positive, it means that the
strategy, the system that you're using,
it has an H in the markets. And of
course, if it's negative, that means you
have a negative H. So what this means is
that you can expect to earn an average
of $26 per trade. So after 100 trades,
you can expect to earn about $2,600. All
right? $26 multiply by 100. Now, let me
show you an example of a negative H.
Again, you can see over here, same
winning rate 70%. Same losing rate 30%.
The only difference now is your average
gain is $10 and your average loss is
$100. And again, plug it into the
formula and you get minus23. So, if you
do this for your trading strategy or
system and you realize that your age,
your expectancy is a negative figure,
then please, right, pause your trading,
pause your investing or whatever you're
doing, right? because you need to dig
deeper to find out whether is this a
strategy you want to be trading longterm
because this means you can expect to
lose an average of $23 per trade and for
most traders this is not something that
you want to to do unless you are doing
this from a high level perspective like
you know you're you're diversifying your
strategies you know to profit in panic
markets you know then that's fine but
again I think most of you watching this
video are not at that level yet so if
you have a negative expectancy a
negative age right this is uh how you
can go about telling whether you have an
H or not. Now, at this point, you might
be thinking, but Raina, you know,
finding an H in the markets is not easy.
Who's going to give me strategies and
systems that has a positive expectancy,
an edge in the markets? I get it, right?
It's not easy. I agree. There's a lot of
work and research that has to be done
for it, right? So, this is why I'm going
to give you this training, this free
54-minute training where you'll discover
three rule-based trading strategies,
trading systems that gives you an edge
in the markets. And it's all backed by
data. I've done all the back testing
works. I'm giving you the exact trading
rules when to buy and when to sell. And
we're covering multiple trading
strategies, right? We're covering a mean
reversion, a trend following, and even a
momentum strategies along with all their
back tested data as you can see over
here for free. Okay? So if you
interested then just go down to my
website tradingwithra.com/go
or I'll put the link somewhere below
this video so you can get access to this
uh training for free. Now moving on
I want to talk about the next thing
which is very important because you can
have an edge in the markets but without
this one thing you will still lose
consistently in the long run and I'm
talking about your risk management. You
must have risk management because this
is what protects your downside no matter
what happens whether you have five or 10
losing trades in a row because without
it even a profitable trading system will
fail. In fact, let me prove it to you
why this is the case. So imagine this.
Imagine there are two traders John and
Sally and let's say they both have the
same trading account, same size,
$10,000.
And let's say they both trade the same
system, a 70% winning rate system with
an average of a 1:1 risk-reward ratio.
This means if you risk $100 on a trade
and you make back $100, that's a 1:1
riskreward ratio. Let's say John risk
$5,000 per trade and Sally risk $100 per
trade and the outcome of the next 10
trades are as follows. You can see over
here lose lose lose followed by win.
So three losses first followed by seven
winners. Now, let me ask you, how much
will John make
after trading? Well, after two trades,
John would have blown up because John
risk $5,000 per trade. So, first trade -
5K, second trade - 5K, and in essence,
he has blown up his account, right?
Faster than I lose an argument with my
wife. Really fast. What about Sally? So,
you can see over here, Sally again
trading the same system. The only
difference is she risk $100 per trade.
So her first three trade, Sally would
have lost $300.
Then because she didn't blow up her
account, she still have funds to
continue trading. She can experience
these next seven wins of $700. And in
total, Sally would have made a profit of
$400 after 10 trades. So you can see
over here, Sally would have made a 4%
return on her account. And the reason
why I'm sharing with you this is because
this shows you the importance of risk
management. Management doesn't matter
what system you're trading, what's the
size of your account. You can have the
same winning rate, the same
risk-to-reward ratio, but if you don't
manage your risk, you will blow up your
account. And remember, your job as a
trader isn't to make money on every
trade. Your job as a trader is to
survive long enough for your age to play
out. Okay? Risk more, survive, and let
your age play out. And now the last
thing that you need is this
discipline. Discipline refers to
following the rules of your trading
system. No matter what happens, whether
you're on a holiday, whether you're
sick, whether you don't feel like it,
whether you have encountered 10 losses
in a row, you still must have the
discipline to follow your rules,
assuming your rules gives you a positive
expectancy and age in the long run.
Because if you don't, then what you're
going to get is inconsistent results.
And often you also experience that
without proper discipline. Even a losing
trading or even a profitable trading
system, right, can still lose you money
in the long run. So here's why. So
imagine this. Imagine this is the
outcome of your next seven trades. Your
first trades, they're all losers. So for
most traders, their thought process is
something along the lines of, you know,
man, I've suffered three losses in a row
now. And then the fourth trading
opportunity comes along and you're
thinking the previous three trades are
losers. This fourth trade is likely to
be a loser as well. I think a better
thing to do is to actually skip the
trade. So that's what you do, right? You
skip the fourth trading opportunity. And
guess what? It turns out to be a winner.
Now at this point in time right shortly
afterwards the fifth trading opportunity
comes along and again the pain of the
recent losses that you have just
experienced is still very raw. You still
feel it. Ah it hurts. So when the fifth
trading opportunity comes along you skip
it again and it turns out to be a winner
winner again.
Next the sixth trading opportunity comes
along and now you're kind of like in a
dilemma right? If you had had you
followed the rules of your system
earlier, you would have, you know,
experienced two winning trades. And now
you look at it. Oh man, the fourth trade
is a winner. The fifth trade is a
winner. So right now the losses is just
around the corner. If I were to take
this trade, it's likely to be a loser as
well. Agree? So what do you do? Well,
you skip the trade and it turns out to
be a winner again. So at this point, you
feel really horrible about yourself. you
have a proven trading system that works
but you keep doubting the rules and
breaking the rules. So now the seventh
trading opportunity comes along and you
tell yourself no matter what you will
follow the rules of your system. You
will enter it because it's a valid buy
signal and that's what you do. So and
the trade turns out to be a winner.
But if you look at it big picture wise
you have experienced three losses and
one winning trade. after seven trades
you have you're still a losing I mean
you've still made losses net losses but
had you follow the exact rules of your
trading system
to take all seven trades you would have
come out ahead positive right because
you have four winning trades versus
three losing trades but because of
discipline because of the inability to
follow your rules you actually lost
money so this is why you must have
discipline not just risk management not
just having and age, but also
discipline, right? Because consistent
actions leads to consistent results. And
if you want to be a consistently
profitable trader, then you must be
consistent with your actions. And that
means being a disciplined trader. Do you
agree? Smash the thumbs up button and
hit subscribe right if you agree.
Now, here are a few scenarios that you
might be experiencing in your trading
journey. Let me just list out all three.
And I'll start with this one over here.
I think most traders are stuck with this
one. You have the discipline. You know
what is risk management, but you don't
have an age. So what you're experiencing
right now is what I call death
by a thousand cuts.
This means that in the long run, your
account value is heading down lower over
time. Not all at once, slowly but
surely. And that's because when you
don't have an H in the markets, but you
have risk management and discipline, you
start to take that 1% loss consistently
over time and that depletes the value of
your account. Next one, you can have an
H plus discipline but no risk
management. So in this case, you find
yourself blowing up your account from
time to time like earlier the John
example where he blew up his account
after two trades. And this other
scenario is where you have an age and
risk management but no discipline. So if
you are in this category then you find
yourself getting inconsistent results.
Sometimes you make money, sometimes you
lose money. And in the long run, you
know, you're not really profitable nor
losing. You're kind of like break even
in the middle of nowhere. So these are
the three common scenarios that traders
will experience, right? When they don't
have either one of the factors. And this
is why I said earlier that you must have
all three to be a consistently
profitable trader. You must have an age,
you must have risk management, and you
must have discipline. This is what I
call the trading success formula.
You must have all three. Not one, not
two, but all three. And when you have
the trading success formula, all right,
you can expect results like this. So
this is the result of a trend following
system since 2000. So this system has
generated about 3,517%
since 2000. For example, in 2014, it's
up 70%, 2015 up 3%, 2018 lost 2%, 2023
lost 19%, etc. So this trading systems
profit right where markets are trending
and as you can see right this alone will
put you in the top 5% of traders because
you are consistently profitable in the
long run. We're looking like you know
over years and not just over a few days
or few months and at the same time right
this will not put you in the top 1% of
traders. Why is that? Because you will
experience draw downs. So for example,
when you just rely on this one system,
this one strategy when market conditions
change, you will go into a draw down
which explains why you will experience
losing months and even losing years
because for a trend following system
when markets become choppy, right, you
will experience losses along the way. So
now the question is how do you then be
in the top 1% of traders? How do you be
a trader who can profit in different
market conditions whether it's a bull
market, a bare market or even during a
recession? And the secret is this. If
you if you want to be in the top 1% of
traders, you must have multiple trading
systems, not just one. Must have, you
know, one or more. The more the marrier
because when you combine multiple
trading systems, you can profit in
different market conditions. So, let me
give you an example. It's like let's say
for example, you run a restaurant
business. You have one restaurant and if
that year economic conditions are bad or
for whatever reasons your restaurant is
not doing well, guess what? All your
income will be tied to that restaurant
and you will likely, you know, lose
money in that year. But what if you have
five restaurants, five different
restaurants selling five different
cuisines at five different locations?
Now, even if one restaurant is doing
poorly, you still have another four
restaurants that could, you know, help
you cushion the losses and still give
you a profitable year, right? Because
you have multiple restaurants under your
belt. And it's the same thing for
trading, right? When you have multiple
trading systems, you increase your odds
of making a profit in a given year. So
here's an example.
So for example, this is the trend
following system I shared with you
earlier. Now let's say you pair it up
with another system. Let's call it MRT,
not the Singapore Choo Choo Train, but
the mean reversion trading system. And
you realize that your results now is a
lot more smoother because you can look
at this third column and see that you're
making a profit almost every single year
and the only losing year you had was
2023, which is a loss of 5%. Other than
that, right, whether it's a dotcom
bubble in 2000, whether it's the 2008
financial crisis, whether it's the 2020
COVID 2022 Russia Ukraine war, you have
been making a profit even in this
difficult market condition. So now, can
you see the importance of having
multiple trading systems and this is how
you be in the top 1% of traders, someone
who can profit in bull and bare markets
even during a recession. So let's do a
quick recap to what we've covered today.
Number one, why traders fail. So many
traders fail because they don't have a
proven strategy. They're strategy
hopping. They can't manage their
emotions and they do things like revenge
trading over overt trading. And as
mentioned earlier, these are not the
cause. These are the symptoms. And these
symptoms exist because you don't have
the trading success formula, which is
you don't have an age risk management
plus discipline. Because if you have it,
then remember my my coin toss example.
You have this magic coin that makes you
money. Every time it's head you win $2,
tails you lose a dollar. Guess what?
You'll be tossing that coin every single
day, right? Whether it's breakfast,
lunch, or dinner, you'll be tossing as
much as possible. You won't have any
discipline issues. And this is how your
trading will be like when you have the
trading success formula. And that alone
will put you in the top 5% of traders.
And if you want to take things further
to be in the top 1% of traders, someone
who can profit almost every single year,
then you need multiple trading systems
because you have different trading
systems that allows you to profit in
different market conditions. Maybe a
system that do well in a choppy range
market, a system that do well in a bull
market, a system that do well in a bare
market. When you have all three, this is
where you own multiple restaurants under
your belt and really will put the odds
in your favor. And again, if you are
interested to learn more about this
different type of trading system so you
can profit in different market
conditions, you can go down to my
website at tradingwithraer.com/go
and grab this uh free 54minut training
where I'll teach you the rules of these
different trading systems. to cover mean
reversion trading, trend following,
momentum, and I'll even give you the
complete trading rules along with the
back test report, the cheat sheet so you
know to implement this trading systems
on your own. So the link over here is at
uh tradinger.com/go.
You can either go down to this link over
here or scan the QR code to get started
right now or I'll put the link somewhere
below this video so you can access it.
Right? So with that said, I wish you
good luck and good trading. I will talk
to you soon.